{"tossups": [{"question": "19th century scholar Franz Mone [[MOH-nuh]] suggested the site of this battle was also the place where the hero of the <em>Song of the Nibelung</em>, Sigurd, slew the dragon Fafnir. Following this battle, a chieftain of the Cherusci [[keh-ROO-skee]] sent the head of his opponent to the Marcomanni to secure an alliance. At Kalkriese Hill, Germanic chieftain Arminius ambushed the forces of Varus, beginning this battle. Emperor Augustus cried \"Give me back my Legions\" following, for ten points, which devastating Roman defeat in the first century?", "answer": "Battle of the <b><u>Teutoburg</u></b> Forest (or die Schlacht im <b><u>Teutoburg</u></b>er Wald; prompt on the \"Varian Disaster\" before \"Varus\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The Cataldo Mission, constructed by the Jesuit missionary Pierre-Jean De Smet, is the oldest building in this U.S. state. In 1905, Frank Steunenberg [[stew-NEHN-burg]], former governor of this state, was assassinated by a disgruntled member of the Western Federation of Miners. In 1992, this state was the site of a standoff between the government and white separatist Randy Weaver at the Ruby Ridge compound, situated near this state's Canadian and Washington border. For ten points, name this state which, during the Civil War, saw a chaotic transfer of its capital from Lewiston to Boise.", "answer": "<b><u>Idaho</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country secured its independence in the aftermath of Operation Storm, which included the retaking of Knin and the expulsion of many Orthodox Christians from Krajina [[krah-YEE-nah]]. During World War Two, a Nazi puppet state in this country was dominated by the Usta\u0161e [[ooh-STAH-sheh]]. This country sought independence from Hungary and unification of its \"Triune Kingdom\" which included Slavonia and the coastal Kingdom of Dalmatia. For ten points, name this former Habsburg territory and constituent country of Yugoslavia, governed from Zagreb.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Croatia</u></b> (or Republika <b><u>Hrvatska</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Russian lieutenant Adam Laxman landed on this island to forcibly return a pair of castaways. Shakushain\u2019s revolt on this island was put down by the Matsumae clan, which was tasked with defending part of it. This island was the location of a short-lived separatist state called the Republic of Ezo, which opposed the Meiji government. In the closing weeks of World War Two, the city of Muroran was bombarded by American ships off the coast of, for ten points, what Japanese island, governed from Sapporo?", "answer": "<b><u>Hokkaido</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ezo</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The lack of convictions surrounding this figure's death led to its site being dubbed \"The Freestate of Tallahatchie\" by the <em>Chicago Defender</em>. Married white woman Carolyn Bryant likely lied that this Black teenager whistled at her. This figure names a 2008 \"Act\" sponsored by John Lewis which aimed to attempt to solve cold cases of violence against Black victims prior to the 1970s. A mid-1950s mob in Mississippi murdered, for ten points, which 14 year old Black teen, whose death galvanized the Civil Rights movement?", "answer": "Emmett <b><u>Till</u></b> (or Emmett Louis <b><u>Till</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The Karsakpay inscription describes how this leader led an army of 200,000 men to subjugate the khan of the Golden Horde, Tokhtamysh [[tohk-tah-MEESH]]. This man captured Ottoman sultan Bayezid the Thunderbolt during the Battle of Ankara. This Turko-Mongolic leader was the direct ancestor of all the Mughal emperors. For ten points, name this conqueror whose name reflects the serious injuries he suffered early in life and who established his capital at Samarkand.", "answer": "<b><u>Tamerlane</u></b> (accept <b><u>Timur</u></b> the Lame, accept Amir <b><u>Timur</u></b>; or <b><u>Tim\u016br</u></b> Gurk\u0101n\u012b)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This tribe negotiated with Maryland Loyalist leader William Bowles, who successfully convinced them to reinforce the British fort in Pensacola during the Revolutionary War. The Seminole were originally from this non-Florida tribe, who migrated to Florida in the 18th century and mixed with local tribes like the Calusa. The militant faction of this tribe, the Red Sticks, were defeated by Andrew Jackson at Horseshoe Bend. For ten points, name this member of the \"Five Civilized Tribes\" of the Southeastern U.S., also known as the Muscogee.", "answer": "<b><u>Creek</u></b> (accept <b><u>Muscogee</u></b> before mentioned; accept Red Stick <b><u>Creek</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This site's monk's cell had a Buddhist style stupa added over a thousand years after its abandonment by inhabitants of the Sindhu Kingdom. A layer of bitumen coated this city's \"Great Bath,\" the earliest public water tank in recorded human history, likely used for religious purposes due to its proximity to the \"College of Priests.\" One of the largest sites of the Harappan Civilization was, for ten points, which city in modern Pakistan whose name translates to \"Mound of the Dead\"?", "answer": "<b><u>Mohenjo-Daro</u></b> (do not accept \"Harappa\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Five miles outside of this city, the first major Protestant victory of the Thirty Years' War occurred at the Battle of Breitenfeld by troops led by Gustavus Adolphus. Nazi Germany modified this city's name to reference a \"Trade Fair\" which ran unimpeded here since medieval times. The dissolution of the Confederation of the Rhine followed Napoleon's defeat at an 1813 battle named for this city, the largest fought during the 19th century. The Monument to the Battle of the Nations is in, for ten points, which city in Saxony, sixty miles from Dresden?", "answer": "<b><u>Leipzig</u></b> (accept Reichsmessestadt <b><u>Leipzig</u></b>; accept Battle of <b><u>Leipzig</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Bernard de Montfaucon [[mont-foh-KOHN]] brought this artwork to the attention of of Europe when he hired Antoine Benoit [[beh-NWAH]] to copy it in its entirety. This artwork, which includes an early depiction of Halley's Comet, depicts Count Guy of Ponthieu [[pohn-TOO]] holding an English king captive for ransom. During the early days of the French Revolution, this artwork was seized by the Directory to be used to cover the tops of military wagons. Harold Godwinson is shown taking an arrow in the eye in, for ten points, which medieval \"Tapestry\" depicting the Battle of Hastings?", "answer": "<b><u>Bayeaux</u></b> [[bah-\"YOU\"]] Tapestry", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Fengtian clique of warlord Zhang Zuolin [[JANG ZHUO-LIN]] was based in this region. The Willow Palisade blocked Han migration into this region. The Lytton Report was produced after the Kwantung Army invaded this region after officers staged the demolition of a section of railroad track in the Mukden Incident. Emperor Puyi was made a ruler of a Japanese puppet state in this region afterwards. For ten points, name this northeastern region of China held by Japan immediately prior to World War Two.", "answer": "<b><u>Manchuria</u></b> (accept <b><u>D\u014dngb\u011bi</u></b> or <b><u>Manchukuo</u></b>, prompt on <b><u>Liaoning</u></b>, <b><u>Jilin</u></b>, or <b><u>Heilongjiang</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A vote on impeaching this governor devolved into the Bloody Monday brawl. This governor recruited prison labor to completely destroy the governor's mansion in order to build a replica of the White House in its place. This man advocated caps on income, inheritance, and net worth in his \"Share Our Wealth\" plan as a U.S. senator, three years before his assassination by Carl Weiss. For ten points, name this \"Kingfish\" who exercised near-dictatorial control over Louisiana from 1929 to 1935.", "answer": "Huey <b><u>Long</u></b> (or Huey Pierce <b><u>Long</u></b> Jr.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A whirlpool off the coast of this country legendarily devoured a boat secured by hemp, wool, and hair ropes during a visit from king Breacan. A 1950s hysteria in this country over \"Jenny with the Iron Teeth\" and the \"Gorbals Vampire\" were traced back to American comic books. This country's folklore includes murderous water horses called \"kelpies\" and seals transformed into human women called \"selkies.\" For ten points, name this country where a dinosaur-like cryptid is said to live in Loch Ness.", "answer": "<b><u>Scotland</u></b> (prompt on \"United Kingdom\" or \"U.K.\"; do not accept or prompt on \"Great Britain\" or \"England\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "After this man broke with other Southern congressmen to oppose the Clayton Compromise, he was stabbed during a fight with state supreme court justice Francis Cone at an Atlanta hotel in 1848. This \"sage of Liberty Hall\" spent most of the Civil War writing both anonymous and signed letters denouncing Jefferson Davis's policy of conscription before leading the Confederate delegation at the Hampton Roads peace conference. For ten points, name this vice-president of the Confederacy.", "answer": "Alexander <b><u>Stephens</u></b> (or Alexander Hamilton <b><u>Stephens</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "An early one of these events on Shrove Tuesday began when white-gowned acolytes carrying red crosses claimed to \u201cextirpate the abusive, perverse customs of Carnival.\u201d These gatherings were often hosted in front of the Palazzo Vecchio, with an image of the devil adorned on top of a pile of straw. Sandro Botticelli legendarily threw his own artwork into the flames during these anti-pagan rituals. The Friar Girolamo Savonarola led, for ten points, which mass burnings of supposedly obscene art in 15th century Florence?", "answer": "<b><u>Bonfire</u></b> of the <b><u>Vanities</u></b> (accept <b><u>fal\u00f2 delle vanit\u00e0</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The 1st Earl of Shaftesbury likely manufactured charges of Catholic sympathies against this Admiralty Secretary, leading to his imprisonment in the Tower of London. This man, who was a member of the entourage of Charles II on his return from the Netherlands during the Restoration, recorded the destruction of St. Paul's Cathedral during a blaze which began on Pudding Lane. The 17th century Great Plague and Great Fire of London were chronicled by, for ten points, which former minister of Parliament who kept a diary that was published to popular acclaim in the 19th century?", "answer": "Samuel <b><u>Pepys</u></b> [[PEEPS]]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A biography accused this author of plagiarizing Emma Langdon Roche in a 1928 article recapping an interview with slave trade survivor Cudjoe Lewis. This author depicted the Southern practice of \"paramour rights\" in her 1934 novel <em>Jonah's Gourd Vine</em>. This author extensively collected Caribbean and southern folklore in books such as <em>Tell My Horse</em> and <em>Mules and Men</em>. For ten points, name this author of a 1937 novel about the Black town of Eatonville, Florida, <em>Their Eyes Were Watching God</em>.", "answer": "Zora Neale <b><u>Hurston</u> </b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, S\u00e9bastien Rale [[RAH-leh]] had a price put on his head by Massachusetts governor Joseph Dudley, who wrongly assumed he had led a raid in Maine. The expulsion of residents who were later dubbed \"Cajuns\" occurred during this war's American theater, known as \"Queen Anne's War.\" The death of the childless Charles II, a member of the Habsburg family, led to this multi-continental war. The Treaty of Utrecht ended, for ten points, what early 18th century war which led to the rise of the Bourbon monarchy in Iberia?", "answer": "War of the <b><u>Spanish Succession</u></b> (accept <b><u>Queen Anne's</u></b> War before mentioned)  In the European theatre of the war, the Duke of Marlborough was partnered with which French-born Austrian general who secured a major victory in the Siege of Turin?  ANSWER: <b><u>Eugene</u></b> of Savoy (or Prince <b><u>Eugene</u></b> Francis of Savoy\u2013Carignano)  <b> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This woman\u2019s feud with doctors during the U.S. Civil War prompted the War</u></b> <b><u>Department to introduce Order No. 351 in October 1863. That order allowed this</u></b> <b><u>woman, in her capacity as the Superintendent of (+)</u> Army Nurses, to appoint female nurses. Prior to this woman\u2019s appointment by the Union Army, this woman penned a bill vetoed by Franklin Pierce to set aside ten million acres to be used for the benefit of the \u201cblind, (*) </b>deaf, and dumb.\u201d For ten points, name this social advocate who created the first generation of U.S. mental asylums.", "answer": "Dorothea <b><u>Dix</u></b> (or Dorothea Lynde <b><u>Dix</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this non-African city, over 80 people were injured after the execution of</u></b> <b><u>Congolese prime minister Patrice Lumumba motivated its population to storm the</u></b> <b><u>Belgian embassy. Suleiman the Magnificent mass-deported this city's (*)</u> Orthodox population to Istanbul and made it the center of the </b><em><b>Sanjak</b></em><b> of Smederevo. Over 100,000 people took to the streets of this city to protest the genocidal regime of Slobodan (*) </b>Milo\u0161evi\u0107 [[mih-LOH-seh-vitch]] in the mid-1990s. For ten points, name this Danubian \"White City\" and former capital of united Yugoslavia, now the capital of independent Serbia.", "answer": "<b><u>Belgrade</u></b> (accept <b><u>Belgrad</u></b>; accept <b><u>Dar Al Jihad</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A note supposedly written by the subject of this event was found in the</u></b> <b><u>wastebasket of Prussian attach\u00e9 Maximilian von Schwartzkoppen, only for that</u></b> <b><u>German officer to later reveal he was in contact with Ferdinand (+)</u> Esterhazy. Following this affair, future prime minister Leon Blum participated in the defense of Emile Zola after he was brought to court for criticizing this treason trial in his pamphlet (*) </b><em>J'Accuse</em>. For ten points, name this anti-Semitic \"Affair\" during the French Third Republic caused by the false prosecution of a Jewish artillery officer.", "answer": "<b><u>Dreyfus</u></b> Affair (accept l'affaire <b><u>Dreyfus</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>It's not a feast, but the Gaelic festival of Lughnasadh [[loo-nah-SAHD]]</u></b> <b><u>traditionally begins with this specific event to commemorate the mother-goddess</u></b> <b><u>Tailte. While held in veneration for Zeus in Classical Greece, scholars speculate the (*)</u></b> <b>Olympics first began as one of these events during its Dark Ages. Aeneas hosts one of these events in book 5 of the </b><em><b>Aeneid</b></em><b> to honor his father Anchises [[ahn-KYE-sees]], who fell during the escape from Troy. In the </b><em><b>Iliad</b></em><b>, events like chariot-racing and (*) </b>wrestling occur during, for ten points, what type of event held after the death of Patroclus?", "answer": "<b><u>Funeral Games</u></b> (prompt on partial answers; prompt on more specific answers like \"Footrace\" or \"Archery Contests\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>This figure, who said \"When the rich think about the poor, they have poor</u></b> <b><u>ideas,\" replaced the Sociedad de Beneficencia with her own namesake foundation. The</u></b> <b><u>Montoneros (+)</u> kidnapped the body of Pedro Eugenio Aramburu in an effort to repatriate this figure's corpse back to her home nation from Spain. This first Argentinian to receive chemotherapy was initially nominated as the vice-presidential candidate for her (*) </b>spouse in the 1952 elections. For ten points, name this actress turned First Lady of Argentina during the mid 20th century known affectionally as \"Evita.\"", "answer": "<b><u>E</u></b>va <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b> (or Mar\u00eda <b><u>E</u></b>va Duarte de <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b>; accept <b><u>E</u></b>vita <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b>; prompt on \"Evita\" alone before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The salutation of the sun by Syrian soldiers under this general was</u></b> <b><u>misinterpreted by the enemy army led by Vitellian as incoming reinforcements,</u></b> <b><u>causing them to break at the Second Battle of Bedriacum. The supposed descendant of</u></b> <b><u>Julius Caesar, Gaius Julius Civilis, rose in rebellion against this leader during the (+)</u></b> <b>Batavian Rebellion. This emperor, who deployed the general Agricola to Britain, also ordered the construction of the (*) </b>Coliseum. The victor of the Year of Four Emperors was, for ten points, which Roman Emperor and founder of the Flavian dynasty?", "answer": "Vespasian (or <b><u>Vespasian</u></b>us; accept Titus Flavius <b><u>Vespasian</u></b>us)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The primary attorney of the defendent in this case, Thomas Addis Emmet,</u></b> <b><u>previously served as barrister for the revolutionary Society of the United Irishmen. In</u></b> <b><u>this case, Attorney General William (+)</u> Wirt argued that the federal patent preemptively applied for by the plaintiff superseded any regulation from the state. Congress's right to regulate interstate (*) </b>commerce was upheld in this 19th century court case. The monopoly of Robert Fulton on New York waters was deemed unconstitutional in, for ten points, which 1824 Supreme Court case?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Gibbons</u></b> v.</em> <em><b><u>Ogden</u></b></em> (accept either)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A month after this work\u2019s premiere, it was re-scored for a performance at</u></b> <b><u>Foundling Hospital. Due to the Duke of Montagu\u2019s insistence on the omission of non-</u><u>martial instruments, this piece's composer was forced to remove the intended (+)</u></b> <b>string parts. Thomas Desaguliers [[duh-sah-gool-YEH]], who was elected to the Royal Society for his artillery research, was fire master at this work's premiere. The signing of a treaty in Aachen is commemorated in this piece, which was commissioned to celebrate the end of the War of the (*) </b>Austrian Succession. For ten points, name this monarch-approved suite by George Frideric Handel.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Music for the Royal Fireworks</u></b></em> (accept <em>Royal</em> <em><b><u>Fireworks Music</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>After one of these parties staged the Anpo Protests, ultranationalist Otoya</u></b> <b><u>Yamaguchi brandished a short sword and killed its chairman on public television</u></b> <b><u>during a debate. \u00c9douard Daladier [[dah-lah-DYEH]], a member of a radical (+)</u> branch of this specific political party, declared war on Germany alongside Britain. The Roosevelt-led New Deal weakened an American iteration of this party, which previously ran Eugene V. Debs for president three times. The party of Hitler ironically dubbed themselves the \"National\" (*) </b>version of this type of party. For ten points, name this generally left-wing type of party that encourages redistribution of resources.", "answer": "<b><u>Socialist</u></b> Party (accept Japanese <b><u>Socialist</u></b> Party; or <b><u>Socialist</u></b> Party of America; or National <b><u>Socialist</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}], "bonuses": []}